<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD GNOME Project: GNOME Development Branch FAQ">
<!ENTITY email "freebsd-gnome">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.gnome">

  <p>This page documents the development model the GNOME maintained software
    follows, and the work flow the &os; GNOME Team uses.</p>
This document is about the development branch.  

  <h2>Contents</h2>
    <ol>
      <li> <a href="#develver">What are development versions all about?</a></li>
      <li> <a href="#develtrack">Should I track development versions?</a></li>
      <li> <a href="#develaquire">How do I obtain development versions of GNOME stuff?</a></li>
      <li> <a href="#develupdate">How do I keep everything up-to-date and in sync?</a></li>
      <li> <a href="#develbroken">What should I do when something does not work?</a></li>
      <li> <a href="#develhelp">How can I help with the development versions?</a></li>
      <li> <a href="#develstate">What is the current state of development GNOME on
	&os;</a></li>
    </ol>

  <h2>Full Text </h2>

    <ol>
<!-- Q1 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="develver"></a>
	<p><b>What are development versions all about?</b></p>
<!-- A1 -->
	<p>The GNOME, MATE, and CINNAMON project all use the same
	  development schema.  The development versions are the packages
	  released by the projects that will eventually become the
	  stable (release) versions.  There are three working branches
	  of development:</p>
	<ol>
	  <li><b>STABLE</b> - The applications and libraries in the stable
	    branch are considered "release quality," and are the versions that
	    appear in the &os; ports tree.  The current stable version are
	    GNOME &gnomever;, MATE &matever;, and CINNAMON &cinnamonver;.</li>
	  <li><b>DEVELOPMENT</b> - In between stable releases are development
	    releases.  Traditionally, GNOME and MATE development releases have
	    odd minor numbers (e.g. 2.3, &gnomedevelver;, 3.(n*2)-1).  Development
	    releases will become stable releases, and move from alpha to beta quality during
	    their lifecycle.  The development releases need testing by &os;
	    users to minimize the number of surprises when the new stable
	    versions are committed to the &os; SVN tree.  At any time the
	    development branch for &os;
	    might be based of a stable GNOME release.  However it will be tagged 
	    "development" here if it is the version that is work in progress by the &os;
	    GNOME team.  The current development branch for &os; is GNOME &gnomedevelver;,
	    MATE &matedevelver;, and CINNAMON &cinnamondevelver;.</li>
	  <li><b>GIT</b> - Often newer-than-new, the GIT master versions of GNOME
	    applications and libraries are alpha quality, or might not even work
	    on &os;. The &os; GNOME project pays attention to, but
	    does not track the alpha quality code.  We do have a build machine
	    that just builds the git code to find build issues.</li>
	</ol>
      </li>

<!-- Q2 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="develtrack"></a>
	<p><b>Should I track development versions?</b></p>
<!-- A2 -->
	<p>If you are looking for a stable environment, absolutely not.  Please
	  only track the GNOME &gnomedevelver;, MATE &matedevelver;, or
	  CINNAMON &cinnamondevelver; branch if you wish to help identify bug
	  and improve the ports for &os;.  You will find little
	  sympathy if a development-quality GNOME application eats your
	  homework.</p>
      </li>

<!-- Q3 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="develaquire"></a>
	<p><b>How do I obtain the development versions of stuff?</b></p>
<!-- A3 -->
	<p>The FreeBSD gnome team uses a GIT repository where we maintain
	  the development versions of the software we maintain of &os;.  These
	  branches contain the complete &os; ports tree plus the development changes.</p>

	<p>How to checkout the new git repo setup.</p>
<!-- xxx explain git layout -->

	<p>During the development cycle, FreeBSD-specific caveats and
	  other useful information will be sent to <a
	  href="mailto:marcuscom-devel@marcuscom.com">
	  marcuscom-devel@marcuscom.com</a>.  If you are tracking
	  the a development branch, you <b>must</b> <a
	  href="http://www.marcuscom.com/mailman/listinfo/marcuscom-devel">
	  subscribe</a> to this list.  You should also consider <a
	  href="http://lists.freebsd.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-gnome">
	  subscribing</a> to <a
	  href="mailto:&email;@FreeBSD.org">&email;@FreeBSD.org</a>.</p>

	<p>In order to help with bug reports, be sure to add the following
	  to <tt>/etc/make.conf</tt> so that gdb back traces contain
	  useful information:</p>
<pre>
WITH_DEBUG="yes"
</pre>
	<p>Please use gdb (from ports) or lldb as a debugger, gdb from
	  base is too old to give usefull results</p>
	<p>GNOME has an excellent guide for getting <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Community/GettingInTouch/Bugzilla/GettingTraces">
	  useful back traces</a>.</p>
      </li>

<!-- Q4 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="develupdate"></a>
	<p><b>How do I keep everything up-to-date and in sync?</b></p>
<!-- A4 -->
	<p>There are two methods of keeping track of what happens in
	  development branches.</p>

	<ol>
	  <li><b>portmaster</b> - Use <tt>portmaster</tt> to update installed ports.  This can be done by telling portmaster where to find the GNOME development checkout.
<pre>
# env PORTSDIR=/path/to/where/the/checkout/is/ portmaster -a
</pre></li>
	  <li><b>poudriere</b> - Build a set of package from the development repository you want to test. See pkg-repository(5) how to configure pkg to use the repo.</li>
	</ol>
<!-- xxx note CONSERVIATE_UPGRADE flag , or pkg upgrade -r GNOME -->

	<p>Keeping your ports up-to-date with the
	  development branch can be complicated.  Sometimes components change
	  in a way that makes <tt>portupgrade</tt> or <tt>portmaster</tt>
	  fail, or causes strange end results. If you plan to track the
	  development branch, it is a good idea to join the
	  <a href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-gnome">
	  freebsd-gnome</a> mailing list, as well as to join the
	  <em>#freebsd-gnome</em> IRC channel on FreeNode
	  (<tt>irc.freenode.net</tt>).</p>

	<p>If all of this sounds scary, or you need a desktop that
	  "Just Works," you should stick with the stable version that
	  is available in the &os; ports tree.</p>
      </li>

<!-- Q5 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="develbroken"></a>
	<p><b>What should I do when something does not work?</b></p>
<!-- A5 -->
	<p>It depends.  If you think the problem is truly a bug with the
	  GNOME component, you can report a bug in the GNOME <a href="http://bugzilla.gnome.org">Bugzilla</a>
	  interface.  If you think the problem lies in a &os; port, or
	  is FreeBSD-specific, send email to
	  <a href="mailto:&email;@FreeBSD.org">&email;@FreeBSD.org</a>,
	  or report the problem on the <em>#freebsd-gnome</em> IRC
	  channel on FreeNode.</p>

	<p>Please forward all relevant bug IDs to
	  <a href="mailto:&email;@FreeBSD.org">&email;@FreeBSD.org</a>
	  so we can keep track of known issues.  Thanks!</p>
      </li>

<!-- xxx this needs more work -->
<!-- Q6 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="develhelp"></a>
	<p><b>How can I help with the development versions?</b></p>
<!-- A6 -->
	<p>Now that work on &gnomedevelver; has started, we need
	  people to install it, and test things.  If you are compiling
	  &gnomedevelver; by hand, be sure to build <a
	  href="&base;/gnome/docs/bugging.html">debugging symbols</a>.
	  Package users will have these symbols already.</p>
      </li>

<!-- Q7 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="develstate"></a>
	<p><b>What is the current state of development GNOME on &os;?</b></p>
<!-- A7 -->
	<p>&gnomever; is the latest version that was merged into the &os; ports tree.  
	  Work is currently underway to make &gnomedevelver; stable.</p>
      </li>
    </ol>
</body>
</html>
